Guide to the Pi Beta Phi, North Carolina Beta Chapter (Duke University) Records, 1929-1988 UA.31.22.0005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pi Beta Phi, North Carolina Beta Chapter (Duke University) records
1929-1988
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pi Beta Phi. North Carolina Beta Chapter (Duke University)
UA.31.22.0005
9.8 Linear Feet
Contains materials relating to the establishment, governance, philanthropy, and campus activities of the North Carolina Beta chapter of Pi Beta Phi fraternity for women at Duke University from 1929-1988. The bulk of material is from 1974-1977 and 1983-1988. Types of materials include manuals, rosters, minutes, photographs, scrapbooks, reports, creative writing, and published materials. Major topics include student life at Duke University, establishing a fraternal organization, pledging, initiation, community service activities, social activities, songs, general governance, leadership, philanthropy, and public relations.
3000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
Provenance
The Pi Beta Phi, North Carolina Beta Chapter (Duke University) Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1980-1990.
Historical Note
From: http://www.pibetaphi.org/ and Petition of Mu Lambda Chapter of Duke University to Pi Beta Phi Fraternity
Pi Beta Phi Fraternity was founded at Monmouth College in Monmouth, Illinois, on April 28, 1867 as a social group for women college students. The fraternity was first known as I.C. Sorosis. The founding chapter disbanded because Monmouth College banned secret societies, and other chapters chose to adopt the new name of Pi Beta Phi in 1888. Pi Beta Phi was the first national secret college society of women to be modeled after the Greek-letter fraternities of men. During a time when few women were admitted to colleges and universities, Pi Beta Phi created a feeling of unity among pioneering women. Some of the symbols of Pi Beta Phi are the golden arrow badge, the carnation, arrowhead pledge pin, and angels. Fraternity history indicates that songs about Pi Beta Phi angels became popular in the late 1930s and early 1940s, and that skits depicting Pi Beta Phis as angels were often used in rush. The colors of the Fraternity are wine and silver blue. The national fraternity supports various philanthropies including Arrowmont (an arts and crafts school), Links to Literacy (promoting lifelong literacy), and Arrow in the Arctic (supporting northern Canadian public libraries). Pi Beta Phi is part of the National Panhellenic Conference.
Mu Lambda Sorority was organized at Duke University on April 22, 1929 by a group of seven women for the purpose of strengthening their bonds of friendship. Mu Lambda pledged three women in fall 1929, and added four more pledges in spring 1930. During the months following the organization of Mu Lambda, its members made a detailed study of the most outstanding sororities which were not on the Duke campus. These sororities sent representatives to interview Mu Lambda. Mu Lambda, advised by Dean Alice Mary Baldwin, decided that Pi Beta Phi was the most desirable sorority. From then on, Mu Lambda attempted to live up to Pi Beta Phi ideals.
Around 1930-1931, to assist with their petition with Pi Beta Phi, six Pi Beta Phis of Durham (alumnae of other schools) organized themselves as an advisory council for Mu Lambda. In 1933, Mu Lambda was accepted into Pi Beta Phi and became the North Carolina Beta chapter. The chapter has been active on Duke campus since 1933 and is governed by the Panhellenic Association at Duke University. Some of their service activities included building a Habitat for Humanity house, serving meals in rest homes, and reading to school children.
Collection Overview
Contains photographs, general orientation materials, guidelines, yearbooks, meeting minutes, scrapbooks, Book of Pledges' Signatures and published materials relating to the North Carolina Beta chapter of Pi Beta Phi fraternity for women. By request of the donor, minutes are restricted to current Pi Beta Phi, North Carolina Beta chapter members. Users must obtain written permission from the North Carolina Beta chapter President to view the minutes.
Related Material
Fraternities and Sororities collection.
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Interfraternity Council. Records.
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Panhellenic Council records.
University Archives, Duke University
Photograph Collection
University Archives, Duke University
Downhower, Laura. Spring Sorority Rush: a Booklet for First-year Women about Rush and Sororities at Duke. 1989.
University Archives, Duke University.
Sororities at Duke: a Booklet to Tell You the Whys and Hows of Rushing. 1953-1968 [serial].
University Archives, Duke University.
Women college students -- North Carolina -- Societies and clubs; Greek letter societies -- North Carolina -- Durham; Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.); Greek letter societies; Pi Beta Phi. North Carolina Beta Chapter (Duke University); Duke University -- Societies, etc.; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.; Pi Beta Phi. North Carolina Beta Chapter (Duke University); Duke University -- History
- Chapter administration, 1932-1982
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains chapter organization history, membership lists, minutes, and a guide for chapter historians. By request of the donor, minutes are restricted to current Pi Beta Phi, North Carolina Beta chapter members. Users must obtain written permission from the North Carolina Beta chapter President to view the minutes. Ordered by alphabetically by folder title. The Petition of Mu Lambda Chapter of Duke University to Pi Beta Phi Fraternity contains profiles of each member, recommendations, and general history of Mu Lambda's petition to join Pi Beta Phi. Ordered alphabetically by folder title.
  - Chapter Historian's manual, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Officers Who Serve", ca 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Membership Directory, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, January 17, 1980-September 22, 1982 RESTRICTED (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Petition of Mu Lambda Chapter of Duke University to Pi Beta Phi fraternity (ca 1932) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Chapter social and philanthropy activities, 1973-1983
  Chapter social and philanthropy activities, ca 1973-1983 Contains creative works, photographs, pledge materials, award for philanthropy, and a guest book from the 50th reunion in 1983. Ordered alphabetically by folder title.
  - Photographs, ca 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pledge materials (songs, mission statements, brief histories), ca 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - President's Award, Retinitis Pigmentosa Foundation, ca 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reunion guest book, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Themes" (member projects), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- History of North Carolina Beta Chapter of Pi Beta Phi (yearbooks) 1929-1988
  Contains yearbooks documenting the social, academic, personal, and philanthropic activities of the North Carolina Beta chapter. The types of materials included in the yearbooks are: photographs, miscellaneous notes, clippings, souvenirs, official statements, creative works, personal narratives, chapter evaluations, and some correspondence. Pages are numbered and in original order. Most yearbooks were bound with string. Two covers were included. Ordered by date.
  - 1929-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1958-1959 Pledge Class (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - September 1971-January 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - February 1972-May 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - September 1974-December 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - September 1974-December 1974, cover (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - January 1975-June 1975, pages 1-40 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - January 1975-June 1975, pages 41-69 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - January 1975-June 1975, pages 70-101 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - September 1975-December 1975, Pages 1-30 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - September 1975-December 1975, Pages 31-40 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - January 1976-June 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - September 1976-December 1976, cover (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - September 1976-December 1976, pages 1-34 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - September 1976-December 1976, pages 35-48 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - January 1977-April 1977, pages 1-28 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - January 1977-April 1977, pages 29-44 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1983-1984, pages 1-20 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1983-1984, pages 21-40 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1983-1984, pages 41-60 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1983-1984, pages 61-69 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - unspecified (Box 2)
  - 1984-1985, pages 1-27 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 1984-1985, pages 28-60 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 1984-1985, pages 61-74 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 1984-1985, cover (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 1985-1986, pages 1-40 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1985-1986, pages 41-82 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 1985-1986, pages 83-99 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - 1986-1987, pages 1-42 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - 1986-1987, pages 43-86 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - 1986-1987, "Senior Farewell Presents: The Graduate" (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Fall 1987 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - 1987, Pledges '87, pages 1-30 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 1987, Pledges '87, pages 31-53 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Spring 1988 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Fall 1988, pages 1-35 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Spring 1988, pages 36-66 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- The Arrow 1980-1986
  The Arrow, published by Pi Beta Phi headquarters, is the fraternity's national public relations and communications tool. The magazine is mailed to alumnae and collegiate members, Greek advisers, university administrators and officers of other international Greek organizations. Ordered by date.
  - Spring 1980-Summer 1981 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Winter 1981-Fall 1984 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Fall 1985-Spring 1986 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Oversized Materials 1933-1985
  - Scrapbook, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - The Arrow, 1974-1981 (Box 3)
  - Records, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Beta, Book of Pledges' Signatures, 1933-1978 (Box 4)
  - History of the Beta Chapter by Anne Boyd, With Correspondence, 1935 (Box 4)
  - The Arrow, 1980, 1984 (Box 4)
  - History of North Carolina Beta Chapter of Pi Beta Phi Fraternity, 1982- 1983 (Box 4)
  - Recording Secretary Book, 1968-1974 (Box 4)
  - Recording Secretary Book, 1974-1978 (Box 4)
  - Pledge Book with Wooden Cover, 1954-1955 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1984 (Box 6)